Alexander Sherikov

CONTACT INFORMATION

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Trondheim, Norway

 $\boxtimes e$ -mail alexander@sherikov.net

☎ phone

http://sherikov.net Latest CV https://github.com/asherikov/cv http://github.com/asherikov Other

https://www.linkedin.com/in/asherikov

SUMMARY

I am an R&D engineer in software and control for autonomous systems with a doctoral degree in humanoid robot control and diverse professional experience in general IT, software quality and architecture, computational software, and robotics frameworks. In particular, I've worked on design and implementation of software for simulation and control of legged, wheeled, and flying robots.

Website

EMPLOYMENT

2019 - present, Senior Autonomy Engineer (UAV), Sevendof, Norway

Onboard software architecture, 3d mapping, simulated and field tests, software quality, cross-compilation, deployment. [C++, ROS, CUDA/Thrust]

Software & Control Engineer (humanoid robots), PAL Robotics, Spain

• Humanoid robot simulation, identification, motion planning, control; numerical optimization. [C++, ROS]

2016 - 2017,Research Engineer (humanoid robots), INRIA, France

Development of a software framework for implementation of optimization-based controllers for humanoid robots. [C++] https://bip-team.github.io/humoto/

2012 - 2016,Doctoral Student (humanoid robots), INRIA, France

• Research in model predictive control of humanoid robots for balancing and locomotion. [C++, MATLAB]

Software Developer (UGV), Örebro University, Sweden 2012 - 2012,

Implementation of a path tracking model predictive controller with obstacle avoidance for an autonomous forklift truck. [C++, ROS, CAN]

2009 - 2010, System & Network Administrator, InfoLan LLC, Russia

Administration of FreeBSD servers and configuration of networking hardware (L2 switches, Cisco Routers) of an Internet service provider.

2006 - 2008,IT Support Engineer, Petrozavodsk State University, Russia

• Web site support, shell scripting.

PERSONAL OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS

- Eigen-based, header-only C++ implementation of Goldfarb-Idnani dual active set algorithm for quadratic programming with double sided constraints and simple bounds: https://github.com/asherikov/qpmad
- C++ reflection/serialization library supporting YAML, JSON, XML, ROS parameter server, and more: https://github.com/asherikov/ariles
- Real-time model predictive controller for Nao humanoid robot and specialized solvers for it: http://sherikov.net/Projects/naowalk.html (master's project)
- ROS development environment for (cross-)compilation, testing, linting, documentation and binary package generation: https://github.com/asherikov/ccws

EDUCATION

2012 - 2016, University of Grenoble, France

PhD in Automatic Control and Production Systems

Balance preservation and task prioritization in whole body motion control of humanoid robots https://github.com/asherikov/phd-thesis/raw/master/asherikov-phd-thesis.pdf

Örebro University, Sweden 2010 - 2012,

Degree Master in Robotics and Intelligent Systems

Model predictive control of a walking bipedal Thesisrobot using online optimization https://github.com/asherikov/ms-thesis/raw/master/asherikov-ms-thesis.pdf

2003 - 2008,Petrozavodsk State University, Russia

Specialist in Information Systems and Technologies

ThesisApplication of multidimensional data structures for indexing of NetFlow records (in Russian)

Summer schools

• Numerical Optimal Control, 04.08.2014 – 13.08.2014, Freiburg, Germany

SKILLS

Applied mathematics

Linear algebra factorizations, pseudoinverses

Numerical optimization quadratic programming, sequential quadratic programming, prioritized least

squares, linear complementarity problems

Control model predictive control, inverse kinematics and dynamics

Modeling rigid body modeling of robots, basics of friction and collision modeling

Robotics

Frameworks ROS, Nao SDK

Dynamic modeling and control RBDL

Simulation / visualization Microsoft AirSim, Gazebo, RViz

Motion planning OMPL

Volumetric mapping OpenVDB, OctoMap UAV controllers PX4, DJI, ArduPilot

Messaging protobuf, mavlink, UAVCAN, CAN, mqtt

Sensors lidar, GPS, ADS-B

Telemetry time-series databases, Grafana, PlotJuggler

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

C/C++ STL, Boost, C++XX, POSIX, pthreads

Computations/CAS Octave/MATLAB, Maxima

Parallel computations CUDA/Thrust
Other shell scripting, python

Programming tools

Compilers/compiler wrappers clang, gcc, nvcc, ccache, scan-build

Version control systems git, SVN
Debugging gdb, lldb, strace

Static and dynamic checks gcc/clang sanitizers, cppcheck, valgrind, clang-tidy

Profilers callgrind, gprof

Testing googletest, googlemock, Boost UTF, ctest Build automation tools catkin, colcon, cmake, make, autotools

Documentation doxygen, PlantUML, graphviz
Packaging FreeBSD ports, dpkg, CloudSmith

Continuous integration Jenkins, Travis

Web-based SCM GitHub, GitLab, GForge

Unix systems administration and networking

Operating systems FreeBSD, Ubuntu

Isolation/emulation docker, qemu, systemd-nspawn, VirtualBox

 $Service\ management \qquad {\rm systemd}$

Computer networks TCP/IP, VLAN, DHCP, DNS, SMTP, Ethernet, routing, switching

 $\begin{array}{ll} \textit{Time synchronization} & \text{NTP, PTP} \\ \textit{Other} & \text{POSIX utilities} \end{array}$

OTHER

Quadratic Programming qpOASES, QuadProg++, ipopt

 $\begin{array}{ll} \textit{Linear algebra} & \textit{Eigen} \\ \textit{Document preparation systems} & \texttt{LATEX} \end{array}$

3D graphics toolkits OpenSceneGraph

Hardware platforms Raspberry Pi, NVIDIA Jetson Nano / Xavier

Languages

• Russian (native)

• English (fluent)

ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

- Reviewer for IEEE T-RO, ICRA, IROS, Humanoids.
- Google Scholar page.

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] D. J. Agravante, A. Cherubini, A. Sherikov, P.-B. Wieber, and A. Kheddar. "Human-Humanoid Collaborative Carrying". In: *IEEE Transactions on Robotics* 35.4 (2019), pp. 833–846. DOI: 10.1109/TRO.2019.2914350. URL: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-01311154.
- [2] D. J. Agravante, A. Sherikov, P.-B. Wieber, A. Cherubini, and A. Kheddar. "Walking pattern generators designed for physical collaboration". In: *IEEE ICRA*. 2016.
- [3] N. Bohórquez, A. Sherikov, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "Safe navigation strategies for a biped robot walking in a crowd". In: *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots*. 2016.
- [4] S. A. Homsi, A. Sherikov, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "A hierarchical approach to minimum-time control of industrial robots". In: *IEEE ICRA*. 2016.
- [5] D. Serra, C. Brasseur, A. Sherikov, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "A Newton method with always feasible iterates for Nonlinear Model Predictive Control of walking in a multi-contact situation". In: *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots*. 2016.
- [6] H. Andreasson, A. Bouguerra, M. Cirillo, D. Dimitrov, D. Driankov, L. Karlsson, A. Lilienthal, F. Pecora, J. Saarinen, A. Sherikov, and T. Stoyanov. "Autonomous Transport Vehicles: Where We Are and What Is Missing". In: Robotics Automation Magazine, IEEE 22.1 (2015).
- [7] C. Brasseur, A. Sherikov, C. Collette, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "A robust linear MPC approach to online generation of 3D biped walking motion". In: *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots*. 2015.
- [8] D. Dimitrov, A. Sherikov, and P.-B. Wieber. "Efficient resolution of potentially conflicting linear constraints in robotics". Preprint. 2015. URL: https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01183003.
- [9] A. Sherikov, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "Balancing a humanoid robot with a prioritized contact force distribution". In: *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots*. 2015.
- [10] A. Sherikov, D. Dimitrov, and P.-B. Wieber. "Whole body motion controller with long-term balance constraints". In: *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots*. 2014.
- [11] D. Dimitrov, A. Sherikov, and P.-B. Wieber. "A sparse model predictive control formulation for walking motion generation". In: *IEEE/RSJ IROS*. 2011.
- [12] A. Sherikov and Y. Bogoyavlenskii. "The use of multidimensional index structures for NetFlow record processing". In: AMICT '07, Proceedings of the Annual International Workshop on Advances in Methods of Information and Communication Technology. 2007.

PARTICIPATION IN RESEARCH PROJECTS

2016 - 2017, COMANOID

- COMANOID ("Multi-Contact Collaborative Humanoids in Aircraft Manufacturing") is a RIA four-year European research project that started in January 2015 as part of the Horizon H2020 program.
- http://comanoid.cnrs.fr/project-overview

2012 - 2016, Romeo 2

- Romeo 2 project is a french research project focusing on Romeo humanoid robot designed by Aldebaran Robotics.
- https://projetromeo.com/

$2012-2012,\ SAUNA$

- SAUNA is a major AASS 3-year project at Örebro University aimed at achieving international excellence in a research area of strong industrial relevance namely, safe autonomous navigation for professional industrial vehicles like forklift trucks, wheel loaders, mining trucks etc.
- https://www.oru.se/english/research/research-projects/rp/?rdb=p693

Grants

2017, Torres Quevedo, Spain

- Torres Quevedo Program (PTQ) Grants for recruiting PhDs
- https://www.ciencia.gob.es/stfls/eSede/Ficheros/2018/RESOLUCION_TORRES_QUEVEDO-2017-1.pdf